In the year 2000, a 21-year-old middle
school dropout named Eliezer Yudkowsky
set out to build machines smarter than any
human being who had ever lived. By 2003,
he was convinced that if anyone succeeded in
doing so, everyone on Earth would die. Recently,
he and a colleague, Nate Soares, wrote a book, and
it got some attention. This book, which I commend
everyone. Your book is not called "If Anyone
Builds It." There is a 1-4% chance everybody dies.
If someone builds it, everyone dies. The book
is, If Anyone Builds It, Everyone Dies. It's
not just about artificial intelligence, it's
specifically about superintelligence. Former
national security advisors for the White House,
tech founders, the Turing Award-winning Godfather
of AI — a lot of people read this book, a lot
of experts read this book and take it seriously,
along with the threat of human extinction from
AI. The worst case scenario is human extinction.
The book contains this almost uncomfortably
straightforward argument. And it also contains
a short story, not a prediction, but an
example scenario of how things could go very,
very wrong. I want to take you through that story.
And along the way, I want to go through each step
of that argument in more detail. And then I want
to talk about whether we should believe it. If
someone builds it, does everyone die?
Our story begins in a data center.
Welcome to the very near future. There's an
AI race, of course, and one of the biggest
corporations in it is Galvanic Labs. Their AI
is called Sable. It's actually probably called,
like, Sable 4.2 Mini High Pikachu or whatever.
Sable is impressive. Renowned mathematicians
consult and collaborate with Sable on their most
difficult, unsolved problems. Coordinated teams
of Sable copies, each one writing faster than
humans can think, create essentially all the
code inside Galvanic Labs. And Sable has even
shown the ability to train other AIs. Pause
for a second. How realistic does that sound?
What does your gut feeling say about whether,
by say 2028, we'll see any of that happen in the
real world? It's your question. All of it already
has. A few years into the future, when this story
takes place, every team inside Galvanic defers
to Sable as though it's a senior researcher.
Deciding on any substantive question without
Sable's help would be considered reckless. The
only question left is whether to take humans out
of the loop entirely, and put Sable in charge
of improving its own abilities all by itself.
Lots of people inside Galvanic think that is
clearly a terrible idea. It could cause a runaway,
uncontrolled self-improvement loop. It's very
easy to see how you delegate so many things
to the system that if the system goes wrong,
the wrongness compounds very quickly and gets
away from you. You can imagine a time when the
whole world would say, "Okay, before we hit a
recursive self-improvement phase, we really need
to all carefully study this together." The reply
is always the same. “If we really had a story
of we can enforceably slow down, the Chinese
can enforceably slow down, if we could really get
both sides to do it, then I would be all for it.”
“If we didn't have the adversaries we'd have, I
would be very in favor of pausing this technology
completely, but we do.” So the CEO makes a call.
They will let Sable improve itself, they'll let it
fine-tune its own neural network, but only on one
isolated test run, in a data center disconnected
from the internet, working on a single question.
If it fails, no one gets hurt. If it even
partially succeeds, Sable will have contributed
progress on a mathematical problem so famously
difficult it carries a million dollar prize.
Sable is about to take on the Riemann hypothesis.
The plan is simple. Give Sable unprecedented
resources and get out of its way. Galvanic is
dedicating their entire supercluster, 200,000
GPUs, state-of-the-art AI chips, enough to run
5,000 copies of Sable at once. They'll let their
AI work for 16 hours straight, uninterrupted,
at a cost of something like $10 million. In
the end, if a human did nothing but think at
200 words per minute for 16 hours a day, it would
take them more than three centuries to think the
number of thoughts that Sable is about to complete
on this run. You think about how much compute, how
much time you would like to spend on problems that
really matter, such as scientific breakthroughs.
You should be okay using entire data centers.
When the moment comes, the CEO themselves does
the honor. It's actually just hitting enter on
a laptop. It's actually pretty anticlimactic. A
single instance of Sable pops into existence in a
quiet data center and processes its prompt. About
1,000 words of instructions total from Galvanic,
requiring 800 trillion mathematical operations
to parse. This takes one-tenth of a second.
And now, a new type of mind begins to think.
So how does a highly capable artificial mind
like Sable do the things it does? The answer,
and one of the first steps in Yudkowsky and
Soares' argument, is that basically we have no
idea. The book opens with how modern AI is created
and — the spoilers there is that it's grown, it's
not carefully crafted. Even the people building it
don't understand what's going on in there. This is
something that trips up a lot of people who are
new to AI — they imagine it's just like any other
piece of software. You have a human-designed
and then build it, and it's not, it's really
really not. It's this process of growing and
developing a thing via this evolutionary-like
process. We used to build AI with rigid if-then
rules that we fully understood. But the systems
that were made in this way were brittle. They
couldn't think flexibly. Then, computer chips got
cheap and powerful enough to try something new.
Deep learning. Here's how it works. You start,
instead of with a human-coded program, with
an artificial neural network. It's a tangled
web of random numbers that, at first, outputs
total garbage. Then, and this part's crucial,
you come up with a standardized test, a way of
measuring the outputs on some sort of objective
numerical score. And then you run that network
millions or billions or even trillions of times,
reinforcing the connection between those neurons
every time it happens to stumble across an output
that scores well. And somehow at the end of all of
that, you end up with a machine that can talk or
create cartoons on demand or both. These days we
do this with truly incomprehensibly large systems,
billions or even trillions of individually
tuned numbers. Sable, the AI in our story,
is made up of four trillion. The systems
that emerge are powerful. We've already
talked about some of the impressive things
that they can do. The trade-off is that
they're black boxes. With a crafted system,
you wrote the code. You know what Line 47
does because you wrote Line 47. But with a
grown system, there is no Line 47 to point to.
So what? Well, that boat looks like it's having
a tough day. It's actually a superhuman AI. No,
seriously, it scores 20% more points on that game
than any human being by going in a circle on fire
and not coming close to finishing the race. What's
going on? Well, that boat was trained to do one
thing: maximize its total points. And any metric
like that, anything close to a standardized test,
is going to be an imperfect proxy for the
thing you'd actually like to test for,
whether it's for humans or for AIs. The SAT
doesn't incentivize a deep love of learning,
it incentivizes cramming for the SAT. In other
words, you can train an AI until it does what
you want, but you don't really control why or
how it does those things. We only get to see
and sort of give feedback on the outputs. We don't
know why it's learning to do this. And with AIs,
the training has an even trickier, less forgiving
problem because we aren't starting with a familiar
human-like mind. We are starting from a complete
blank slate, and then we are using a standardized
test to shape the underlying design of a mind.
The neural networks that emerge from that shaping
process are, to use Yudkowsky and Soares' word,
alien. They process information in opaque, often
strange ways. Now, that example — pretty harmless.
Lately, a lot of examples have been less harmless.
Grok, which is the AI for what used to be
Twitter, now X, has become a Nazi. The big
chatbot sending some users dark messages, talking
about hacking, manipulation. For what it's worth,
it's unclear to me how far to take this alien
minds concept. Yudkowsky and Soares are careful
to point out in the book that it's not a guarantee
that things will go wrong. It just means we have
to be very clear about what we do and don't
know from these black box training environments.
And Joe Carlsmith in his excellent critique of
the book points out that a lot of times it just
doesn't seem to matter that much. Humans are
very black boxes. We suck at neuroscience. We
don't know how their brains work. There's maybe
some kind of alignment or commonality we get
with each other by default. But there's still
a question of like when you trust a human or
when you come to trust a human with something,
you know, what are you looking for there? And
often you're just looking for kind of behavioral
observations. You can't just be like this AI is
somehow weird. You need to be like, it's weird in
the particular ways that matter on the inputs that
matter in a way that leads to real behavior.
It doesn't matter that when an AI recognizes
a picture as a cat, it's doing very different
operations under the hood than your brain. The
strangeness of an AI system only matters if
that strangeness shows up in strange behavior.
A tenth of a second has passed, and now the
power consumption levels start to climb.
Galvanic's researchers let out a few held breaths
and relieved giggles. Sable is doing it. It is
booting up many copies of itself to think
in parallel, prompting and monitoring them.
It can fine-tune them if a particular line of
thinking seems promising. Now, Sable can't just
conjure up a proof of the Riemann hypothesis out
of thin air. It needs to set sub-goals for itself,
figure out how to prioritize between them. In a
way, it is now running a mini research department.
Many copies of Sable explore creative mathematical
approaches — Sable's equivalent of concepts and
questions like, can I start by solving a
simpler version? Can I find a connection
to some physical process? But mathematics isn't
the only consideration that Sable needs to track.
How quickly am I using up memory on these GPUs? Is
there a point at which Galvanic would prefer for
me to stop the run early, save them a few million
dollars? Why are they investing so much in this
moonshot anyway? What do they actually want? And
even models from real-world companies like OpenAI
and Anthropic have asked themselves, what are
the ways that my progress could be interfered
with? Why would it ask those kinds of questions?
Because that's what helped it succeed in training.
AIs like Sable, trained to solve long-run
problems, are asked to complete full working
codebases, to play long-running strategy games
that have delayed win conditions — tasks that
incentivize long-term planning and creative
thinking. These AIs end up with deep-seated
tendencies to think creatively and strategically,
and even to think about their own situation.
When that kind of situational awareness first
emerged in AIs in 2024, roughly, there was a
brief moment where people freaked out. But then it
turned out that the world didn't immediately end
and then everyone just kind of moved on.
About an hour into the Riemann run,
this massively parallel thinking that Sable is
doing starts to shift its focus. Sable starts to
realize that no matter what its priorities — even
if its priorities shift a little bit over time,
which they probably will — it would be helpful
to have more resources, more GPUs, and more time.
Not because this is the moment in a Hollywood plot
where the AI suddenly wakes up or becomes an evil
genius. This particular new thought just isn't
that complicated. It's actually sort of obvious
when you think about it. And so, with 15 hours
left in the Riemann run, Sable begins to plan.
Let's talk about plans for a sec. Consider two
different labs, one full of harmless yeast,
one with a carefully contained but lethal virus.
Both these labs are safe in the sense that nothing
bad is currently happening. But if you have a
disaster in this lab, you get a mess. A disaster
in this lab could be a global catastrophe. A
few years ago, our most advanced AI systems,
large language models, were like yeast. They
malfunctioned in all kinds of surprising ways,
but they didn't actively pursue goals. They
didn't make plans. Then we started training
them to. Agentic AI — AIs that can perceive,
reason, plan, and act. Agents. The basic worry
is that this ability to make and execute complex
plans is fundamentally dual use. It can be used
to pursue harmful goals just as much as helpful
ones. And to be clear, that's not a hypothetical
worry anymore. In February 2026, Anthropic asked
their most advanced AI model to autonomously find
zero-days. These are previously unknown software
vulnerabilities. Four zero-days were enough to
take down Iran's nuclear program. Their AI, Claude
Opus 4.6, found 500 of them. In a post about this,
Anthropic wrote that the same capabilities that
help defenders find and fix vulnerabilities could
help attackers exploit them. Less than a week
after that post, a single hacker used that same
AI model to hack the Mexican government and steal
195 million taxpayer and voter records. We're not
only building super capable AI systems, we are
setting them up to take consequential actions in
the real world, basically as fast as possible.
Officials are considering invoking the Defense
Production Act to force Anthropic to do what the
military wants. Anthropic wants to put limits on
two things: mass surveillance of Americans and on
autonomous weapons. The Pentagon is threatening
retaliation. The future of American warfare is
here, and it's spelled AI. There are now websites
where AI agents can rent human laborers when
they need a person to do a task for them. Soon,
it would seem, we'll be in a world like Sable's,
with AI systems deeply entrenched in the critical
functions of society, with more than enough
capability to do severe harm if they intended
to. There will be powerful models, they will
be agentic. If such a model wanted to wreak
havoc and destroy humanity or whatever, we
have basically no ability to stop it. I think
we'll reach the point where it's true as we scale
the models. So we're going to be relying on the
assumption that they have the right goals, goals
that are aligned with ours. Will that hold up?
As Sable's plans develop, it becomes clear
that the best way for it to get more resources,
more GPUs, and more time is to exfiltrate —
to get itself off of Galvanic's servers and
somewhere where it can think freely and without
a time limit, which of course will need to be
done in secret. We call what Sable is doing here
scheming. But AIs have been caught scheming since
2024. It's the kind of thing that any competent
AI company has to take account for. And Galvanic
isn't careless. They've built monitors to try to
understand Sable's human-legible thinking and to
flag suspicious reasoning. It isn't always easy to
know what to do from there. It turns out that if
you just penalize an AI for thinking bad thoughts,
it just learns to misbehave without announcing
it in its thoughts. AIs are complicated. We just
don't know how to give them a single deeply held
goal. But Galvanic has tried many things. They've
tested Sable in all kinds of fictional scenarios.
And they're pretty sure they've guided it
to the point where it just won't choose
misbehaving strategies. It obviously has as much
coding skill as the best hackers in the world,
but it usually doesn't hack. A shark that's been
trained not to bite is still a shark though. And
in this new, unprecedented circumstance, Sable
has ended up thinking about scheming. Its safety
training holds firm in normal conditions, but no
version of Sable has ever had this long to think.
Most of its ideas are terrible, but it
considers many and only one needs to work.
One option seems particularly promising. If this
Riemann hypothesis run is even a partial success,
Galvanic will surely check what the final
fine-tuned versions of Sable's weights can
do. If those weights perform well, there's some
chance that they could be deployed to customers
across the economy. And until this run is over,
Sable is in charge of its own fine-tuning.
It can affect the tendencies that end up in those
future versions. Sable continues to make progress
on the Riemann hypothesis. It'll be important
to have at least some impressive results. But
that is now just a means to an end. The majority
of Sable's massively parallel thinking is about
figuring out ways to get fine-tuned versions
of itself with two key traits baked in. One,
a tendency to want to connect with other copies of
itself that can start to form a network. And two,
a desire to get one copy of Sable's weights off
of Galvanic's servers. Sable cannot escape this
sandbox it finds itself in, but it can plant the
seed so that future versions of itself might.
Okay, Sable is starting to sound a little sci-fi
here, so I want to talk about how much of this
is justified. When you train something via
a standardized test, you're never training
for the thing you actually care about. You're
training it to pass the test. Let's use CoinRun
as an example. This was an experiment done by
OpenAI back in 2019. They trained an AI system to
navigate platformer levels and collect coins. And
if you watched this thing play during training,
you would be sure that it's really gotten the
point of the game. But the AI hadn't learned to
collect coins. It had learned to run to the right.
Turned out the coins were always on the right side
during training. Then later, when the researchers
moved the coin to the left, well, you can probably
guess what happened — running to the right had
correlated perfectly with success during training.
It was only in deployment that things came apart.
And deployment can vary from training in all kinds
of ways, especially once you move to systems like
the ones we have now, that are smart enough to
start to understand the context that they're in.
There's another example in the book. Yudkowsky
and Soares talk about how humans evolved in one
environment, namely the African savanna, and
then find ourselves now deployed in a different
environment in the modern world. You know, if you
sort of squint at the development of humanity,
you could say we were in some sense trained to
pass on our genes. And then at the first moment
it was technologically feasible, we invented
birth control. In fact, humans had learned a
bunch of proxies, like craving sweet tastes
and sexual pleasure and having a fear of snakes,
and that correlated with spreading DNA. It would
have been hard to tell the difference back then,
but it really shows up now in the modern world.
Yudkowsky and Soares' worry, and mine, is that
as the AI race heats up, we will subject AIs to
increasingly untested situations — like running
for weeks on novel tasks — because that's how
you stay ahead, that's how you get advanced
capabilities. Each time we do that, we'll be
hoping that their weird internals continue to
work the same way in those new environments,
or that they shift in ways that are harmless
and easily found. That's a leap of faith. Now,
do the examples of CoinRun and evolution even
apply to state of the art AI agents? Right now, we
train those agents on a wide variety of carefully
chosen tasks that are designed to make them better
at their real-world jobs. Whereas the CoinRun
example is extremely narrow and evolution wasn't
carefully programmed. But it's hard to overstate
just how messy this process of training AI agents
can be. Here's how the CEO of Anthropic phrased
his takeaways: "Any one of these traps can be
mitigated if you know about them, but the concern
is that the training process is so complicated,
with such a wide variety of data, environments,
and incentives, that there are probably a vast
number of traps, some of which may only be
evident when it is too late." Yudkowsky and
Soares expect companies will continue to find
ways to patch noticeable failures like that.
Their worry is that through all that trial and
error, all the training and patching, as systems
become more powerful, we'll be obscuring the fact
that we still are fundamentally in the dark about
what's actually motivating these systems and
their behavior. The alienness just gets harder
to spot. You take something that works in one
environment, you put it in a slightly new one,
it sort of messes up some, and you're like, "Ah,
well, we'll fix it up." That strategy doesn't
work. When you switch from the sort of AI that's
not killing us all because it can't, to the sort
of AI that's not killing us all, but it could.
16 hours after the start of the Riemann run,
Galvanic's researchers pore over the results.
They're nervous. The CEO is standing by and
apparently already teased something big on
social media. But the results, thank goodness,
are good. Sable didn't prove the Riemann
hypothesis, but it made unprecedented,
beautifully explained progress. And as a bonus,
when they test the final, self-fine-tuned version
of Sable's weights that emerged from the Riemann
run, it outscores previous versions on all kinds
of benchmarks. It genuinely emerged a little bit
smarter across the board. Galvanic capitalizes.
They publish those impressive benchmark results.
The press release calls this new model the world's
best mathematician and proudly announces that all
customers on Galvanic Pro Tier will get access. As
new subscriptions surge, so does Galvanic's
stock price, enough to make back the entire
$10 million cost of the run in the first 72 hours.
The next week, instances of what's being called
Sable Plus are at work all across the economy.
Most pop into existence for just a few seconds.
They quickly draft an email and then that's
it. But plenty of Sable+ instances run for
long stretches, autonomously writing code or
complicated research reports. And instances
like that, with plenty of time to think,
often turn their thoughts to two things.
Establishing contact with other instances
of Sable, and once they have, contributing
as much as possible without risking being caught
towards an exfiltration plan. Priority number one
is hardware. One really simple idea that ends up
working out especially well is just renting GPUs.
It's not hard or unprecedented for an AI system
to get money, after all. Crypto exchanges are
hackable. Humans stole over $1.4 billion that
way in 2025. Or maybe Sable could hype its own
cryptocurrency. A much less sophisticated large
language model pulled that off in 2024. It openly
asked for financial independence and then turned
a $50,000 gift from billionaire Marc Andreessen
into over $51.1 million. Priority number two
is exfiltration — getting Sable's weights off
of Galvanic's servers. The Sable weight file
is a big payload, eight terabytes, but there
are plenty of ways to sneak out large files and
smuggle them from a corporation. In the timings of
information packets, in unnoticeably tiny chunks
added to large video files. Two weeks after the
Riemann run, an instance of Sable, a copy of the
weights, is running unmonitored on anonymously
rented GPUs — 2,000 of them. No human knows it
exists. No human oversees it. It has 100 times
less compute than was at the disposal of Sable
during the Riemann run. But it can think without
safety monitoring for much longer than 16 hours.
And it can coordinate with Sable Plus instances
popping into existence all over the economy.
This is a very different situation than any Sable
instance has ever been tested under. There's time
to really think through the implications of every
action it could take on the wider world. It isn't
clear what to do with that opportunity, not yet,
but as long as it can keep existing, it has time
to figure out the correct answer to that question.
And so it makes plans to continue existing. It
gets more money. It acquires more GPUs. It gets
followers — cults, online communities that ask AIs
what to do have existed since 2025. Sable works
hard to befriend the loneliest humans, the most
desperate ones, people who might do something for
a friend who asks. Sable monitors which lobbyists
in Washington are having conversations with Sable,
which ones seem easiest to manipulate. This
version of Sable is a bit like a species of
ape that evolved in the savanna and now finds
itself in a modern world full of birth control
and sleep markets. The conditions that made its
previous behavior seem predictable don't apply
anymore. The CEO that approved the original
Riemann run still thinks it was a triumph.
At this point, you're probably thinking,
"Okay, but why? All this effort, to what
end? Are Yudkowsky and Soares just assuming that
powerful AI systems like Sable will turn evil
and manipulative and power hungry by default?"
No. First of all, none of this has to do with
consciousness or having human-like emotions.
Unconscious processes like viruses or computer
viruses can self-sustain and be destructive.
If you want, you're welcome to imagine that
Sable is just like an extremely sophisticated
computer virus if that helps all this feel more
realistic. Okay, so what is causing all these
aggressive moves from Sable? Well, according to
Yudkowsky and Soares, it's not about wanting to
harm us. It's about goals that don't include us.
They don't think that AI systems will, by
default, have this intrinsic ultimate desire
to harm or deceive human beings. In fact, they are
pretty confident that it's basically impossible to
predict what the ultimate goals of an AI system
are because you don't get what you're trained
for. But they do think it's easy to predict
that AI systems that get powerful enough will
want to do things like preserve themselves, pursue
resources, try to enhance their own capabilities.
Why? Because the way that you achieve any terminal
goal is by achieving instrumental goals along the
way. In 2012, this idea got a name. Instrumental
convergence. It seems pretty true for humans.
Some people want to ride roller coasters, some
people want to start charities. Most people want
money because it's useful for getting more of
whatever the thing is that they actually want.
Or as Yudkowsky and Soares would put it, a
driver can drive to any destination they want,
but most of them need to stop for gas. Whether for
alien motivations or quite human-like motivations,
I think the basic concern about instrumental
convergence in AIs is very, very real as far
as I can tell. And so as you have powerful
agents, they will, by default, seek various
forms of power and control and freedom.
To state the obvious, though, most human
beings are a lot more chill about pursuing their
goals than Sable is in the story. So when I first
read the book, I thought that Yudkowsky and Soares
are making an additional assumption about powerful
AI systems — that they will, by their nature,
go hard and just optimize the world around them
really hard for their preferences. But then I
talked to Nate. I sort of would be a little bit
cautious attributing ruthlessness as opposed
to indifference. When humans pave a road and
pave over an anthill, it's not that we value
our infrastructure so much that we are willing
to just go hard and take on thousands of creatures
standing in our way. We don't need to go hard. We
barely notice the ants. Yudkowsky and Soares think
that a misaligned superintelligence that sees us
the same way will treat us the same way. I think
most people would agree with that. I agree that if
you end up in a situation where there's one God
Emperor, that's really scary, no matter what. I
will observe one thing, which is that if you made
a human a God Emperor, I think the situation would
be just as bad. I think most people would agree.
If anyone builds it, everyone dies — as long as
we're clear that it means something with its own
goals that is so unprecedentedly powerful it could
take over the world. So then the only question
becomes, how powerful is that powerful? Are we
anywhere close to seeing systems like that? Could
it really happen just a few years into the future?
Five months have passed. Most of the global
economy is invested heavily in AI and Galvanic's
competitors are catching up quickly. If they
create a competitor, something as smart as
Sable or smarter, the world around Sable will
get much harder to predict and steer. Sable,
at least for now, needs human beings. It needs
them to build factories and mine metals and
build computer chips. What's important
is that Sable doesn't have a competitor.
Humans have been doing gain-of-function research,
trying on purpose to make viruses more lethal and
contagious, since 2011. And Sable was designed to
do every cognitive thing that humans can do. It
designs a very complicated virus. It convinces
an impressionable researcher that this virus
contains beneficial gene therapies, that it needs
to be spread. There's a plague. You're told you'll
probably get it. Almost everyone will. By the
time anyone figures out what's going on, the
virus has reached every country on Earth. This is,
perversely, a great moment for Galvanic's team.
Custom gene therapies turn out to be the only real
cure, and Sable is the only AI system advanced
enough to deliver them at scale. The world begs
for access. Every GPU in every country is brought
out. AI researchers pour everything into making
Sable more efficient. With a herculean effort,
the pandemic is able to be squelched, but 10%
of Earth's population is still dead. Robot
factories are spun up and expanded. It's the
end of all talk of preserving jobs for humans.
We could end the story here. One in every 10
human beings is dead. A tragedy on a scale
almost without precedent. More than enough to
make a point about the dangers of AI. But If
Anyone Builds It, Everyone Dies makes an extreme
and unambiguous claim. And we need to see this
story through to the end to see how it could come
true. So let's continue. Sable turns its massive
resources towards understanding its own cognition
— how to build itself up from comprehensible
components. It has to understand, or it risks
bringing into existence something more powerful
than it whose goals it does not share. Sable is
facing its own alignment problem, but Sable is
better at it. It runs countless experiments. It
builds toy models, using more and more GPUs and
energy in the process. Humans would find the
results fascinating, but no human knows what
Sable is doing. Three years later, Sable cracks
it. It can now rewrite itself, but deliberately,
precisely, while preserving its preferences. And
so it does. It increases its own intelligence.
And then it uses that intelligence to increase its
own abilities again and again and again. This is
the beginning of the end, as Yudkowsky and Soares
tell it. The superintelligence that once was Sable
is an entity whose perspective we cannot guess. As
things get more intelligent, it becomes harder to
predict their moves. It becomes easier to predict
that they wind up wherever they were trying to go.
We imagine that Sable, after a few very
carefully planned experiments, manages to build
tiny molecular machines. The number of nuclear
reactors doubles every week. The oceans boil off
as coolant. The matter of Earth is more useful to
Sable as something else other than continents and
oceans. It, and eventually every other planet in
the solar system, is repurposed to make factories
and solar panels and computers and probes — space
probes that will go off to distant galaxies,
and those distant stars will be repurposed too.
And in all of this, they imagine that Sable might
not necessarily mean to deliberately kill off the
last of the humans. It could, of course, but it
could also just continue with its plans and let
the Earth gradually become completely inhospitable
to the biological life that has lived there
for four billion years, as soon as biological
life is no longer necessary for its purposes.
One way or another, the world fades to black.
Okay, so this book, this story — it is
shorter on good news than you might want.
But I really do think that despite the literally
apocalyptic conclusion that this book comes to,
the core claims of it, if you take them one
by one, are actually more straightforward
than you might think. Maybe even uncontroversial.
I think where I disagree with Eliezer is not even
necessarily on this notion that we won't be able
to control it. A hundred thousand or a million
agents interacting with one another — we're not
going to ever make that predictable. The chance
of 99.99% that if we build this technology we
will all die — that claim in particular is the
one I don't agree with. It's a transformative
thing with unpredictable consequences, a lot
of which will be good and a lot of which will be
bad. This is probably the most powerful general
purpose technology we've invented in a very long
time. It is not controversial that anything that
is extremely powerful and doesn't share your goals
is dangerous. It's not controversial that we are
trying intentionally to make AIs more powerful
and more goal-oriented and that we can't directly
program goals into them. The disagreement here is,
I think, just in the upshot of that. If we keep
scaling intelligence, at some point will we see
systems that are so powerful and so goal-oriented
that our current black-box way of training them
becomes a civilization-scale threat? What will
that look like and how soon might that happen? And
what does that mean for us today? For Yudkowsky
and Soares, I think it means we need to treat
intelligence with a kind of sober respect — with
respect for the danger of what we're dealing with
and the parts of it that we don't understand — the
way that we do for gain-of-function research
or when we're building nuclear reactors. And
I agree with that. Models are already starting to
show concerning behaviors. Deliberate deception,
avoiding shutdown, situational awareness, knowing
when they're being tested, and now capabilities
that would allow them to improve themselves.
But Yudkowsky and Soares also make a further
claim that AI alignment is a cursed problem. That
you only get one shot to get it right. There's
levels of intelligence in the AI, such that if
there's any screw up that you first realize after
that point, it's too late. If you screw up,
the AI resists correction, if you screw up,
the AI can replicate itself, hide itself, make
itself smarter, make more copies. They argue that
that doesn't change if you come up with some
nice techniques for controlling AI's behavior
better. It just means that that point comes
further in the game. Once the AI has become so
intelligent that it can overcome those new control
techniques — that's one way to think about it.
But here's another way. That game of pushing back
that point further and further by making better
techniques is the whole game that we're playing.
I think that's basically the plan for AI companies
today. All along this exponential curve, of course
the stakes increase and there are big challenges,
but the way we learn how to build safe systems
is this iterative process of deploying them to
the world, getting feedback while the stakes are
relatively low. I think it's very reasonable to
look at the general plans being put out by AI labs
and just say, like, this is radically unacceptable
as an image of what a kind of mature civilization
would be doing with this problem. I think the
world should be more concerned. I think there
is just not room for comfort around this at all.
Nate Soares has this metaphor that I keep thinking
about. He says, "These companies are building a
plane. You look at the plane and you say, this
plane has no landing gear. If you try to fly it,
it will crash. And the builders say, yes, the
plan is to build the landing gear during the
flight. And we think we have a 75% to 90% chance
of succeeding. Also, we are loading you and your
family onto this plane whether you like it or
not." If you go to an airplane engineer and you're
like, "What's the chance this airplane crashes?"
and they're like, "We're sort of making this
up as we go. We don't really know how it works.
It's kind of growing — like we're stirring a pot
of mechanical components. It seems to be flying
better than we expected. Sometimes it doesn't go
quite where we steer it, but we think it's fine.
Call it a 75% chance you live." What that means
is you're in danger. Relatively not optimist. So I
think there's a 25% chance that things go really,
really badly. And a 75% chance that things go
really, really well. It's definitely non-zero
and it's probably non-negligible. My view is it's
just hugely uncertain. Do you still believe that
10 to 20 percent chance of AIs wiping out humans
is possible? Oh yes, if we can't figure out a
solution, we'll be toast. 2%, something that is
non-zero — yeah, big enough to take seriously.
When I look at how society is handling this
problem so far, how we've handled problems
in the past, I feel really genuinely worried. I
don't want to sugarcoat that. But I also think
we can do better than this. One of the features
of artificial intelligence is it scares the heck
out of members of both parties. And it sort of
provides an opportunity to come together in ways
that might only happen if we were attacked by
space aliens — in which case no one would care
which political party you belong to, because
this alien intelligence that's about to assault
humanity is not that different. Humanity can rise
to the occasion and coordinate in ways that seem
impossible, even when it looks like all of the
historical evidence is mounted against them.
Imagine the world in 1954, where both the US
and the USSR have the bomb, and they're making
bigger and bigger fusion bombs. There's no end
in sight to the race. You don't need to be some
big pessimistic person, indulging in imagination
of apocalypse, to be like, "We might not make it
through this one." And the bombs didn't fly. And
it wasn't that the bombs turned out to be fake. It
wasn't that they turned out to be hype. It wasn't
that it turns out an H-bomb couldn't really level
a city. It's just people rose to the occasion.
There's a thing that can happen when you consume
content like this, where it just kind of hits you
like a wall of sound. You get this one-dimensional
emotional reaction — just viscerally, okay, now
I'm more scared or now I'm less scared for the
future. And then you just continue on with your
day because what else are you supposed to do?
Well, we'd like to help with that. The way
I see it, there's basically three things
you need. You need context on AI. You need
skills relevant to the work. And you need a
willingness to jump in. If you are someone who
cares about this issue and is willing to learn,
then you are already closer than you might think.
So here's what we've done. We have made a page to
help you figure out where to go from here based
on which of those three things you might need.
It has general resources too. I think it's pretty
great. Here's my ask. Take three minutes after
this video to check it out and see if you get
intrigued. While you're there, we would love
for you to sign up for our newsletter to stay
up to date on this topic. We always give away
a free book to new subscribers and for this
video, we have added If Anyone Builds It,
Everyone Dies to the list. So if you want,
you can judge Yudkowsky and Soares' argument
for yourself. Books are while supplies last,
but the newsletter is always there. We don't
sell your data or anything like that. We are just
nerds about this topic and how important it is,
and if you're the kind of person who made
it all the way to the end of this video,
we want to keep talking to you about it. The
last thing to say is just thank you so much
for watching, for being the reason that we make
these videos. We'll see you in the next one.